<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/</id>
  <title>Thợ Code - Blog</title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[Tiếng nói của giai cấp Công nhân Lập trình]]></subtitle>
  <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-06-21T11:08:03+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thợ Code</name>
    <uri>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/</uri>
  </author>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/privacy-notice/</id>
    <title>Privacy Notice</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<!--StartFragment-->
<p>This Privacy Notice and its Addendum(s) (“<strong>Privacy Notice</strong>”) describe how Grab Holdings Inc, its respective subsidiaries, affiliates, associated companies and jointly controlled entities (collectively “<strong>Grab</strong>”, “<strong>we</strong>”, “<strong>us</strong>” or “<strong>our</strong>”) collect, use, process and disclose your Personal Data through the use of Grab’s mobile applications and websites (respectively “<strong>Apps</strong>” and “<strong>Websites</strong>”), as well as products, features and other services globally, operated by Grab (collectively, “<strong>Services</strong>”).</p>
<p>This Privacy Notice applies to our consumers, agents, vendors, suppliers, partners (such as driver, delivery and merchant partners), contractors and service providers (collectively “<strong>you</strong>”, “<strong>your</strong>” or “<strong>yours</strong>”).</p>
<p>“<strong>Personal Data</strong>” is any information which can be used to identify you or from which you are identifiable. This includes but is not limited to your name, nationality, telephone number, bank and credit card details, personal interests, email address, your image, government-issued identification numbers, biometric data, race, date of birth, marital status, religion, health information, vehicle and insurance information, employment information and financial information.</p>
<p>We typically collect, use, disclose or otherwise process your Personal Data in accordance with this Privacy Notice with your consent, or in compliance with applicable laws, such as where:</p>
<ul>
<li>it is required for us to comply with legal requirements;</li>
<li>it is required for us to enter into or perform a contract with you; and/or</li>
<li>for our legitimate interests or the legitimate interests of any other persons, including but not limited to for the purposes set forth in this Privacy Notice.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>I.      COLLECTION OF PERSONAL DATA</strong></p>
<p>We collect (and may combine) Personal Data about you in the ways listed below:</p>
<p><strong><em>You provide your Personal Data to us</em></strong></p>
<p>We collect your Personal Data when you provide it to us. For example, when you:</p>
<ul>
<li>complete a user profile or registration forms (such as your name, contact information and other identification information where needed);</li>
<li>provide information to assess your eligibility to provide services as a Grab driver partner or delivery partner (such as your driver’s license information, vehicle information and background check results);</li>
<li>interact with our social media pages (such as your social media account ID, profile photo and any other publicly available data);</li>
<li>participate in contests or events organised by us (such as the pictures, audio, or videos you may submit, which may include images of yourself);</li>
<li>verify your identity through various means (such as social media logins, submission of selfie images or independently verified payment card information);</li>
<li>fill up demographic information in surveys (such as your age, gender, and other information you may volunteer such as your marital status, occupation and income information); and</li>
<li>agree to take a ride with in-vehicle audio and/or video recording features.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>When our Services are used</em></strong></p>
<p>Personal Data may be collected through the normal operation or use of our Apps, Websites and Services. Some examples are:</p>
<ul>
<li>your location information;</li>
<li>feedback, ratings and compliments;</li>
<li>transaction information (such as payment method);</li>
<li>information about how you interacted with our Apps, Website or Services (such as features used and content viewed);</li>
<li>device information (such as hardware model and serial number, IP addresses), file and app names and versions, GPS location, IMEI number, and advertising identifiers or any information that may indicate device or app modification);</li>
<li>
<p>telematics data (such as your speed, acceleration and braking data);</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>we work with partners to install telematics devices in rental vehicles for the following purposes:</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>to ensure that vehicles are maintained appropriately and serviced in a timely fashion;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>to help maintain the safety, security and integrity of our Services;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>to improve and enhance our Services; and</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>for internal tracking of the vehicle, analysis and administrative purposes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>these partners own and share such telematics data with us:</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>our partners are also contractually obliged to safeguard this data.personal data you enter in messages when you use our in-app communication features; and</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>personal data you enter in messages when you use our in-app communication features; and</li>
<li>
<p>personal data that may be captured through your interaction with us, our agents, in-vehicle audio and/or video recording during a ride (such as your image or voice or both, and its related metadata).</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>our in-vehicle applications or devices</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>we may install in-vehicle audio and/or video recording applications or devices to promote the safety and security of our driver partners, delivery partners and consumers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>your Personal Data may be captured in these audio and/or video recordings. Where in-vehicle audio and/or video recordings are made, such recordings are collected, processed, used and stored in a manner in accordance with this Privacy Notice and applicable laws.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Do note that some Grab partners may install personal in-vehicle applications or devices in their vehicles for their own purposes, which may result in your Personal Data being captured by them during the course of use of our Service. This practice is not endorsed nor prohibited by Grab, and the collection, use and disclosure of Personal Data obtained from personal in-vehicle applications or devices is the responsibility of the relevant partner. Please check with the relevant partner if you have any quires about their use of personal in-vehicle applications or devices.</p>
<p><strong><em>From other sources</em></strong></p>
<p>When we collect Personal Data, including but not limited to your name, contact information and other identification information where needed from other sources. Such sources include:</p>
<ul>
<li>referral programmes;</li>
<li>our business partners, such as fleet partners, payment providers, ride-hailing partners and transport partners;</li>
<li>insurance and financial providers;</li>
<li>credit bureaus, alternative credit scoring agencies and any other credit reporting organisations;</li>
<li>publicly available or governmental sources of data;</li>
<li>when our users add you as an emergency contact;</li>
<li>when our users add you as a recipient or beneficiary of any use of our Services;</li>
<li>when you use our in-app chat; and</li>
<li>marketing services providers or partners.</li>
</ul>
<p> <strong><em>Sensitive Personal Data</em></strong></p>
<p>Some of the Personal Data that we collect may be sensitive in nature. This may include Personal Data pertaining to your race, national ID information, religious beliefs, background information (including financial and criminal records, where legally permissible), health data, disability, marital status and biometric data, as applicable. We collect sensitive Personal Data only with your consent and/or in strict compliance with applicable laws. In the event that you are required to furnish any documentation or information to us for any Purpose which may contain such sensitive Personal Data (which is not required for that Purpose), you agree to redact such sensitive Personal Data before providing such documentation or information to us.</p>
<p><strong><em>When you provide Personal Data of other individuals to us</em></strong></p>
<p>In some situations, you may provide Personal Data of other individuals (such as your spouse, family members or friends) to us. For example, you may add them as your emergency contact, when you use the in-app chat or when you add them as recipients or beneficiaries of any use of our Services. If you provide us with their Personal Data, you represent and warrant that you have obtained their consent for their Personal Data to be collected, used and disclosed as set out in this Privacy Notice.</p>
<p><strong><em>Personal Data of minors</em></strong></p>
<p>As a parent or legal guardian, please do not allow minors under your care to submit Personal Data to Grab. In the event that such Personal Data of a minor is disclosed to Grab, you hereby consent to the processing of the minor’s Personal Data and accept and agree to be bound by this Notice and take responsibility for his or her actions.</p>
<p><strong>II</strong>.    <strong>USE OF PERSONAL DATA</strong></p>
<p>Grab may use your Personal Data for the following purposes set out in the list below. (“<strong>Purposes</strong>”). Additionally, if you use Grab in various capacities (for example, if you use multiple Grab Services, or if you are both a driver partner/delivery partner and a consumer), we may link your Personal Data collected across your various capacities to facilitate your use of our Services and for the Purposes described below:      </p>
<p><strong><em>Providing services and features</em></strong></p>
<p>Your Personal Data will be used to provide, personalise, maintain and improve our Apps, Websites and Services. This includes using your Personal Data to:</p>
<ul>
<li>engage you to provide you with Services across our various business verticals;</li>
<li>create, administer and update your account;</li>
<li>process, manage or verify your eligibility for or application of Services, promotions, rewards and subscriptions with Grab;</li>
<li>conduct due diligence checks and risk assessments / analysis;</li>
<li>verify your identity and age (where necessary);</li>
<li>validate your ride and process payments;</li>
<li>offer, obtain, provide, facilitate or maintain insurance or financing solutions;</li>
<li>track the progress of your trip and detect abnormal trip variations;</li>
<li>personalise your Apps experience (such as to recommend products and services relevant to you, identify your preferences or otherwise personalise your experience with Grab);</li>
<li>make your experience more seamless, such as automatically filling in your registration information (such as your name or phone number) from one Service to another Service or when you participate in our surveys;</li>
<li>perform internal operations necessary to provide our Services, including troubleshooting software bugs and operational problems, conducting data analysis, testing and research, monitoring and analysing usage and activity trends;</li>
<li>protect the security or integrity of the Services and any facilities or equipment used to make the Services available;</li>
<li>enable communications between our users;</li>
<li>invite you to participate in our surveys and studies;</li>
<li>enable our partners to manage and allocate fleet resources; and</li>
<li>fulfil the services to you as a data processor, where you have provided consent to the data controller (i.e. the organisation you had purchased goods or services from, and for whom Grab is providing services on behalf of) for such services to be rendered. </li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>Safety and security</em></strong></p>
<p>We use your data to ensure the safety and security of our Services and all users. This includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>screening driver and delivery partners before enabling their use of our Services;</li>
<li>identifying unsafe driving behaviour such as speeding, harsh braking and acceleration, and providing personalised feedback to driver partners;</li>
<li>verifying your identity when you log in to Grab;</li>
<li>using device, location, profile, usage and other Personal Data to prevent, detect and combat fraud or unsafe activities;</li>
<li>sharing drivers and passengers of driver partners’ location and details when the emergency button or the “Share My Ride” feature is activated; and</li>
<li>monitoring compliance with our terms and conditions and policies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>User support</em></strong></p>
<p>We use Personal Data to resolve user support issues. For example, we may:</p>
<ul>
<li>investigate and address concerns;</li>
<li>monitor and improve our user support responses;</li>
<li>respond to questions, comments and feedback; and</li>
<li>inform you about steps taken to resolve user support issues.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>Research and development and security</em></strong></p>
<p>We may use the Personal Data we collect for testing, research, analysis and product development. This allows us to understand and analyse your needs and preferences, protect your Personal Data, improve and enhance the safety and security of our Services, develop new features, products and services, and facilitate development of insurance and finance solutions.</p>
<p><strong><em>Legal purposes</em></strong></p>
<p>We may use the Personal Data we collect for legal purposes, such as to investigate and resolve claims or disputes, detect/prevent/prosecute crime, or as allowed or required by applicable law.</p>
<p>We may also use your Personal Data when we are required, advised, recommended, expected or requested to do so by our legal advisors or any local or foreign legal, regulatory, governmental or other authority.</p>
<p>For example, we may use your Personal Data to:</p>
<ul>
<li>comply with court orders or other legal, governmental or regulatory requirements;</li>
<li>enforce our Terms of Service or other agreements; and</li>
<li>protect our rights or property in the event of a claim or dispute.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>Marketing and promotions</em></strong></p>
<p>We may use your Personal Data to send you marketing communications relating to customised products or services (that may be of interest or relevance based on your profile), or Grab’s partners’, sponsors’ and advertisers’ products, services, events or promotions. For example, we may:</p>
<ul>
<li>send you special offers that may be of interest or relevance to you across all of Grab’s service offerings;</li>
<li>send you alerts, newsletters, updates, mailers, promotional materials, special privileges, festive greetings; and</li>
<li>notify, invite and manage your participation in our events or activities.</li>
</ul>
<p>We may communicate such marketing to you by various means, where applicable (including by SMS, chat applications (e.g. WhatsApp, Telegram, LINE, Viber, WeChat, Zalo)), push notification, call, and by email).</p>
<p>If you wish to unsubscribe to the receiving of such marketing communications, please click on the unsubscribe link in the relevant email or message. Alternatively, you may also update your preferences in our Apps settings. Please note that while you may opt out of marketing or promotion communications, Grab may still send you service-related messages (such as information on your transactions, rewards, etc.).</p>
<p><strong><em>User Published Content</em></strong></p>
<p>If you publish content (such as a review or comment) on Grab’s platform, it will be shown publicly along with your personal data (such as profile name, uploaded photo(s)), and other information you choose to include in your content. For more information, see our <a href="https://www.grab.com/vn/en/terms-policies/ugc-terms-reviews/">Review Guidelines</a>.</p>
<p><strong>III.    DISCLOSURE OF PERSONAL DATA</strong></p>
<p>We need to share Personal Data with various parties for the Purposes. These parties include:</p>
<p><strong><em>Other users</em></strong></p>
<p>For example: </p>
<ul>
<li>If you are a passenger of driver partners, we may share your username, pick-up and drop-off locations with our driver partner fulfilling your Service request;</li>
<li>If you are a driver partner, we may share your Personal Data with your passenger including your name and photo; your vehicle make, model, number plate, location and average rating;</li>
<li>If you are a delivery partner, we may share your Personal Data with your selected merchant and user, including your name and photo; your vehicle make, model, location and average rating;</li>
<li>If you are using our GrabExpress Service, we may share your Personal Data with the recipient of your parcel, and vice versa, as well as the delivery partner in charge of fulfilling your service request; and</li>
<li>If you use our in-app chat, we may share your mobile number and Grab-registered name with the other parties to your chat.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>With third parties</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>With third parties related to your use of Grab Services</em></strong></p>
<p>For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you are a passenger of driver partners, we may share a vehicle’s location and driver’s and/or your name with third parties when you use the “Share My Ride” feature or activate the Emergency Button.</li>
<li>If you are a driver-partner, we may disclose your vehicle plate number or other personal data to the insurance company and/or to your passenger for the purpose of submission of insurance claims..</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>With the owner of Grab accounts that you may use</em></strong></p>
<p>For example, your employer may receive trip data (tagged as business rides) when you use your employer’s Grab for Business account.</p>
<p><strong><em>With subsidiaries and affiliates</em></strong></p>
<p>We share Personal Data with our subsidiaries, associated companies, jointly controlled entities and affiliates. The companies in the Grab group share resources, such as infrastructure and technology, with each other to provide you with a consistent, relevant and secure experience when you use our Services, and for the Purposes set out in this Privacy Notice.</p>
<p>For example, we do this to make your experience more seamless, such as by automatically completing your registration information from your use of one Grab’s Service when you sign up for a new Grab Service.</p>
<p><strong><em>With Grab’s service providers and business partners</em></strong></p>
<p>We may provide Personal Data to our vendors, consultants, marketing partners, research firms, and other service providers or business partners. This includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>payment processors and facilitators;</li>
<li>debt collectors;      </li>
<li>credit bureaus, alternative credit scoring agencies and any other credit reporting organisations;</li>
<li>background check and anti-money laundering service providers;</li>
<li>cloud storage providers;</li>
<li>advertising and marketing partners and platform providers;</li>
<li>data analytics providers;</li>
<li>research partners, including those performing surveys or research projects in partnership with Grab or on Grab’s behalf;</li>
<li>educational and training institute partners;</li>
<li>fleet and merchant partners;</li>
<li>insurance and financing partners;</li>
<li>third party intermediaries involved in the managed investment of funds, such as brokers, asset managers, and custodians;</li>
<li>service providers who perform identity verification services; and</li>
<li>vehicle solutions partners, vendors or third-party vehicle suppliers.</li>
</ul>
<p>For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you requested a service through a Grab partner or used a promotion provided by a Grab partner, Grab may share your Personal Data with that Grab partner.</li>
<li>If you have rented a vehicle from our recommended fleet partners to drive with Grab, we may share relevant information (e.g. the status of your account, applicable incentives/promotions, your ride statistics) for collaborative efforts (e.g. create new incentives and benefits for you or improving supply of driver partners).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>With our legal advisors and governmental authorities</em></strong></p>
<p>We may share your Personal Data with our legal advisors, law enforcement officials, government authorities and other third parties. This may take place to fulfil the legal purposes (mentioned above), or any of the following circumstances:</p>
<ul>
<li>where it is necessary to respond to an emergency that threatens the life, health or safety of a person; or</li>
<li>where it is necessary in the public interest (e.g. in a public health crisis, for contact tracing purposes and safeguarding our community).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>Business transfers</em></strong></p>
<p>We may share your Personal Data with other parties, in connection with any acquisitions, sales, mergers, joint ventures, consolidation, restructuring, financing or any other type of business transactions. Your Personal Data will however remain subject to our obligations made in any pre-existing Privacy Notice that you have agreed to.</p>
<p><strong>IV.    RETENTION OF PERSONAL DATA</strong></p>
<p>We retain your Personal Data for the period necessary to fulfill the Purposes outlined in this Privacy Notice unless a longer retention period is required or allowed by law. Once your Personal Data is no longer necessary for the Services or Purposes, or we no longer have a legal or business purpose for retaining your Personal Data, we take steps to erase, destroy, anonymise or prevent access or use of such Personal Data for any purpose other than compliance with this Privacy Notice, or for purposes of safety, security, fraud prevention and detection, in accordance with the requirements of applicable laws.</p>
<p><strong>V.   INTERNATIONAL TRANSFERS OF PERSONAL DATA</strong></p>
<p>Your Personal Data may be transferred from country, state and city (“<strong>Home Country</strong>”) in which you are present while using our Services to another country, state and city (“<strong>Alternate Country</strong>”).</p>
<p>When we transfer your Personal Data from your Home Country to the Alternate Country, we will comply with our legal and regulatory obligations in relation to your Personal Data, including having a lawful basis for transferring Personal Data and putting appropriate safeguards in place to ensure an adequate level of protection for the Personal Data. We will also ensure that the recipient in Alternate Country is obliged to protect your Personal Data at a standard of protection comparable to the protection under applicable laws.</p>
<p>Our lawful basis will be either consent (i.e. we may ask for your consent to transfer your Personal Data from your Home Country to the Alternate Country at the time you provide your Personal Data) or one of the safeguards permissible by laws.</p>
<p><strong>VI. COOKIES AND ADVERTISING ON THIRD PARTY PLATFORMS</strong></p>
<p><strong><em>Cookies</em></strong></p>
<p>Grab, and third parties with whom we partner, may use cookies, web beacons, tags, scripts, local shared objects such as HTML5, advertising identifiers and similar technologies (collectively, “<strong>Cookies</strong>”) in connection with your use of the Websites and Apps, which may be persistent or stored only during an individual session on your browsers or devices.</p>
<p>Cookies may have unique identifiers, and reside, among other places, on your computer or mobile device, in emails we send to you, and on our web pages. Cookies may be used for various purposes such as to:</p>
<ul>
<li>provide the essential, basic functions of the use of our Websites, Services or Apps;</li>
<li>authenticate you, or remember your user preferences and settings;</li>
<li>delivering and measuring the effectiveness of advertising campaigns, such as by measuring number of views or clickthroughs;</li>
<li>analyse site traffic and trends;</li>
<li>serve you relevant advertisements across other apps and websites owned by other companies (whether by us or by other advertisers); and</li>
<li>enhance user interface and experience by generally understanding the online behaviors and interests of users who interact with our Website, Services or Apps.</li>
</ul>
<p>Grab may allow third parties to use Cookies on the Websites and Apps to collect the same type of Personal Data for the same purposes Grab does for itself. Third parties may be able to associate the Personal Data they collect with other Personal Data they have about you from other sources. We do not necessarily have access to or control over the Cookies they use.</p>
<p><strong><em>Disabling the collection of cookies on our websites</em></strong> </p>
<p>You have the right to choose to disable, block or deactivate cookies. Please note that however refusal or removal of some cookies could affect the availability, functionality or use of our Website, Services or Apps.</p>
<p>You may adjust your internet browser settings to disable, block or deactivate cookies, delete your browsing history or clear the cache from your internet browser. The settings may be contained within the “History”, “Preferences”, “Settings” or “Privacy” section of your internet browsers, or you may otherwise consult the help section of your internet browser for more information.</p>
<p><strong><em>Disabling the display of Targeted Ads through our App</em></strong> </p>
<p>We may facilitate the display of targeted advertising on other platforms, such as on other online platforms that you may be a user of.</p>
<p>You may be able to limit our use of your Personal Data to display targeted advertisements on behalf of our advertisers, by adjusting your preference through the Apps. Depending on the type of phone and operating software that you are using, you may be granted the option to disable our use of mobile identifiers (such as Apple’s IDFA or Google’s GAID) and the ability to track you across apps and websites owned by other companies by adjusting the settings available on your mobile devices. Through adjusting the settings on your device, you can typically reset, delete, limit and/or otherwise restrict the use of such mobile identifiers.</p>
<p>Although we will not use your Personal Data to show you such targeted advertisements on other platforms, you may still see generic ads that appear relevant to you. This may be because we have engaged third party advertisers / platforms to display ads to users of specific attributes or demographic makeups who may find them relevant. You may be able to limit seeing these advertisements through managing your preferences on these platforms.</p>
<p><strong>VII. Protection of Personal Data</strong></p>
<p>We will take reasonable legal, organisational and technical measures to ensure that your Personal Data is protected. This includes measures to prevent Personal Data from getting lost, or used or accessed in an unauthorised way. We limit access to your Personal Data to our employees on a need to know basis. Those processing your Personal Data will only do so in an authorised manner and are required to treat your information with confidentiality.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, please understand that the transmission of information via the internet is not completely secure. Although we will do our best to protect your Personal Data, we cannot guarantee the security of your Personal Data transmitted through any online means, therefore, any transmission remains at your own risk.</p>
<p><strong>VIII.   YOUR RIGHTS WITH RESPECT TO YOUR PERSONAL DATA</strong>    </p>
<p>In accordance with applicable laws and regulations, you may be entitled to:</p>
<ul>
<li>inquire about the processing of your Personal Data and be provided with a copy of it;</li>
<li>in some cases, request the correction and/or deletion of your Personal Data;</li>
<li>in some cases, request the restriction of or object to the processing of your Personal Data;</li>
<li>withdraw your consent to the processing of your Personal Data (where we are processing your Personal Data based on your consent);</li>
<li>request receipt or transmission to another organisation, in a machine-readable form, of the Personal Data that you have provided to us where we are using your Personal Data based on consent or performance of a contract; and</li>
<li>complain to the relevant data privacy authority if your data privacy rights are violated, or if you have suffered detriment as a result of unlawful processing of your Personal Data.</li>
</ul>
<p>Where you are given the option to share your Personal Data with us, you can always choose not to do so. If we have requested your consent to processing and you later choose to withdraw it, we will respect that choice in accordance with our legal obligations.</p>
<p>However, choosing not to share your Personal Data with us, withdrawing your consent to our use of it or to your agreement with our Privacy Notice could mean that we are unable to perform the actions necessary to achieve the purposes of processing described in <em>Section II (Use of Personal Data)</em> or that you are unable to make use of the Apps or the Services.</p>
<p>After you have chosen to withdraw your consent, we may be able to continue to process your Personal Data to the extent required or otherwise permitted by applicable laws and regulations.</p>
<p>We will screen and verify all requests beforehand. In order to verify your identity and/or authority to make the request, we may require you to provide supporting information or documentation to corroborate the request. Once verified, we will give effect to your request within the timelines prescribed by applicable laws.</p>
<p><strong>IX. AMENDMENTS AND UPDATES</strong></p>
<p>Grab may modify, update or amend the terms in this Privacy Notice at any time. Such amendments shall be notified to you through the Apps and/ or other appropriate means  at least five (5) business days before the effective date. The updated version will be posted on the website <a href="http://www.grab.com/vn/en/th/enen/">http://www.grab.com</a>. It is your responsibility to review the Privacy Notice regularly. Your continued use of the Apps, Websites or Services, or continuing to communicate or engage with Grab following the effective date of the modifications, updates or amendments to this Privacy Notice , whether or not reviewed by you, shall constitute your agreement to be bound by such amendments.</p>
<p><strong>X. HOW TO CONTACT US</strong></p>
<p>If you have any queries about this Notice or would like to exercise your rights set out in this Notice , please fill-in the <strong><a href="https://privacyportal-apac.onetrust.com/webform/c039f7fe-1e11-4137-9d03-2d647d9fbcee/bba6bcbc-b6a7-4c52-ac74-4a51d659350d">following form</a></strong> or direct your mail to our Data Protection Officer. :</p>
<p>For users in Philippines,\
Name: MyTaxi PH Inc (Attention : Grab Privacy Office)\
Address: Level 27&amp;28 Exquadra Tower – Lot 1A Exchange Road corner Jade Street, Ortigas Center Pasig City, Philippines</p>
<p>For users in Thailand,\
Name: Grabtaxi (Thailand) Co., Ltd. (Attention : Grab Privacy Office)\
Address: 1550 Thanapoom Tower, 30th Floor, New Petchburi Road, Makkasan Sub-District, Ratchathewi District, Bangkok 10400, Thailand </p>
<p>For users in other countries,\
Name: c/o Grab Holdings Inc. (Attention : Grab Privacy Office)\
Address: 6 Battery Road, #38-04 Singapore 049909</p>
<p>In order for us to attend to your queries expeditiously, we prefer that inquiries be made via the online form.</p>
<p>The original of this Notice is written in the English language. In the event of any conflict between the English and other language versions, the English version shall prevail.</p>
<hr />
<p><strong>ADDENDUM 1: GRAB FOR BUSINESS</strong></p>
<p><strong>I. INTERPRETATION</strong></p>
<p>All capitalised terms but undefined terms used herein shall bear the same meaning as those defined in the Terms of Use and Grab’s Privacy Notice.</p>
<p>This Addendum forms part of the Privacy Notice. In the event of any inconsistency between the Privacy Notice and this Addendum, this Addendum shall prevail.</p>
<p><strong>II. GRAB’S RELATIONSHIP WITH USERS AND CLIENTS</strong></p>
<p><strong><em>How Grab for Business works</em></strong></p>
<p>Grab for Business is provided as an add-on feature to facilitate corporate billing for the Authorised Users’ use of Grab’s Services in the course of work.</p>
<p>When an organisation (“<strong>Client</strong>”) chooses to utilise Grab for Business, the Authorised User is given the option of tagging his/her rides or other transactions to the Client or to tag it as a personal ride. An Authorised User is referred to in the Privacy Notice as a passenger of driver partners.</p>
<p>As part of this feature, Grab will disclose detailed trip and booking information that Authorised Users have tagged as being for business purposes to the Client. Apart from this, Grab does not disclose other Personal Data of its Authorised Users to the Client.</p>
<p>Alternatively, an individual user may choose to set up a business profile within the Apps to facilitate the tagging of business-related rides and to generate consolidated trip reports to facilitate the submission of claims from his or her employer. When used in this mode, the claims process is user-driven and the user’s employer need not be a Client.</p>
<p>For ease of reference, Authorised Users and individual users will each be referred to as a “User” and collectively as “<strong>Users</strong>” in this Addendum.</p>
<p><strong><em>Grab is a data controller, so are our Clients</em></strong></p>
<p>In respect of any User and the processing of all their Personal Data (including but not limited to Linking Data and Portal Data), <strong>Grab acts as a data controller</strong>. For further information on how Grab collects, uses and discloses Users’ Personal Data, please refer to the Privacy Notice.</p>
<p>Due to the way Grab for Business works, Grab does not process any Personal Data for and on behalf of the Client. Accordingly, <strong>Grab is not the data processor of the Client</strong>, but <strong>an independent data controller</strong> in respect of all Personal Data that it processes in the course of providing the Grab for Business feature. Likewise, the Client is an independent data controller of the Personal Data (e.g. the Linking Data and Portal Data) that it discloses to and/or receives from Grab.</p>
<p>As independent controllers, Grab and the Client individually determine the purposes and means of processing Personal Data, subject to the provisions set out in the Terms of Use and this Privacy Notice. Grab and the Client are also individually responsible to ensure the protection of Personal Data under their charge.</p>
<p><strong>III.</strong>   <strong>WHAT PERSONAL DATA IS COLLECTED, PROCESSED AND DISCLOSED</strong></p>
<p><strong><em>What Grab collects as part of Grab for Business</em></strong></p>
<p>In order to provide the Grab for Business feature, the individual user or the Client will be required to provide the following information about the Authorised User to Grab:</p>
<ul>
<li>full name;</li>
<li>business email address; and</li>
<li>other identifying information about the Authorised User as reasonably requested by Grab.</li>
</ul>
<p>Grab will use this information for the purposes of:</p>
<ul>
<li>authenticating the User;</li>
<li>where applicable, linking the Authorised User’s account with the Client’s Grab for Business account or tracking the Authorised User’s business profile bookings on the Apps, as the case may be;</li>
<li>where applicable, verifying the Corporate Billing status of such Authorised User from time to time; and</li>
<li>contacting the User in accordance with the purposes set out in the Privacy Notice .</li>
</ul>
<p>Upon onboarding such User to the Apps, Grab will process the Personal Data of the User in accordance with the Privacy Notice and this Addendum.</p>
<p><strong><em>What Grab discloses to its Clients</em></strong></p>
<p>Grab will disclose relevant trip and booking information as determined by Grab from time to time to the Client to facilitate Corporate Billing.</p>
<p><strong><em>What Grab discloses to its individual user</em></strong></p>
<p>Depending on the business profile settings selected by the individual user, the user may retrieve and generate reports containing his/her relevant trip and booking information.</p>
<p><strong>IV.    PARTIES’ OBLIGATIONS</strong></p>
<p>The Client and Grab shall each:</p>
<ul>
<li>individually inform their data subjects of how each processes Personal Data and allow their data subjects to exercise their rights under the local data protection/data privacy laws;</li>
<li>comply with the obligations applicable to each party under the applicable data protection/data privacy laws when processing any Personal Data of the Proposed or Authorised Users;</li>
<li>obtain the necessary consents (if applicable) to facilitate the provision of the Grab for Business feature; and</li>
<li>implement appropriate legal, technical and organisational measures to protect Personal Data against unauthorised or unlawful processing and against unauthorised loss, destruction, damage, alteration, or disclosure, as well as any breach or attempted breach of each party’s security measures (“<strong>Information Security Incident</strong>”).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>ADDENDUM 2: GRABDEFENCE PRIVACY STATEMENT</strong></p>
<p>This Privacy Statement (“<strong>Statemen</strong>t”) describes how GrabTaxi Holdings Pte. Ltd., its respective subsidiaries, affiliates, associated companies and jointly controlled entities (collectively “<strong>Grab</strong>”, “<strong>we</strong>”, “<strong>us</strong>” or “<strong>our</strong>”) collect, use, process and disclose data through use of GrabDefence and its related services (“<strong>GrabDefence</strong>”).</p>
<p>Grab provides its customers (“<strong>GD Customers</strong>”) with the GrabDefence service that helps to prevent, detect, and combat fraud or unsafe activities on their platforms and applications (such as web-based and mobile applications based e-commerce platforms) (“Digital Platforms”). GD Customers will integrate GrabDefence into their Digital Platforms to proactively capture data which helps to identify potentially fraudulent activities on their Digital Platforms.</p>
<p>This Statement applies to the users of GD Customers’ Digital Platforms (“<strong>you</strong>”), and strictly relates to the data collected, used and disclosed on behalf of GD Customers for the purposes of providing GrabDefence. Kindly refer to the applicable terms of service and/or privacy notices of the GD Customers to understand how they otherwise collect, use and disclose your data.</p>
<p>Please note that GrabDefence only collects information from the users of GD Customers’ Digital Platforms, details of which are shared in this statement.</p>
<p><strong>I.    COLLECTION OF DATA</strong></p>
<p>To provide GrabDefence to GD Customers, information from your device and information relating to your use of GD Customers’ Digital Platform will be collected. Such information include device identifier information (such as IMEI, Android ID, MAC address etc), device and hardware information (such as device name, screen size etc) as well as other contextual data in relation to your use of GD Customers’ Digital Platforms (such as IP address, Wifi address, GPS location data, etc).</p>
<p>We may combine the information we have collected to derive insights on a particular device (for example, insights on whether there are signs of app modification, data manipulation, device tampering, GPS spoofing). We do not attempt to personally identify you based on the information above in order to provide GrabDefence to GD Customers.</p>
<p>The information on your device that we collect above is done when you interact with GD Customers’ Digital Platforms, for example, when you launch the Digital Platform on your device or when you make a transaction on the Digital Platform. Such collection will be done in accordance with the GD Customers’ terms of service and/or privacy notices.</p>
<p><strong>II.    USE OF DATA</strong></p>
<p>We generally process your information on behalf of GD Customers in order to assist with their fraud detection efforts. It is up to the GD Customers’ sole discretion to apply the outcome derived from the use of GrabDefence on their Digital Platforms.</p>
<p>In this regard, we may use, combine and process your information for the following purposes (“<strong>Purposes</strong>”):</p>
<ul>
<li>providing, operating and maintaining GrabDefence;</li>
<li>investigating faults with, and troubleshooting, GrabDefence;</li>
<li>research and development for GrabDefence, including but not limited to improving existing features and services, or developing new features and services, for GrabDefence;</li>
<li>detecting patterns in the datasets collected to gather insights on fraudulent activities;</li>
<li>regulatory and internal audit compliance purposes; and</li>
<li>responding to any law enforcement request or court order.</li>
</ul>
<p>Please be assured that the information collected of your device will not be used by Grab for any marketing efforts or combined with any other datasets available to Grab in a manner that unfairly prejudices you.</p>
<p><strong>III.    DISCLOSURE OF DATA</strong></p>
<p>We may need to share information with various parties for the Purposes. These parties include:</p>
<ul>
<li>GD Customers, with whom you are registered as a user;</li>
<li>Our subsidiaries and affiliates;</li>
<li>Our service providers (for example, we use Amazon Web Services’ cloud to host your information); and</li>
<li>Our legal advisors, law enforcement officials and government authorities.</li>
</ul>
<p>Save for the abovementioned parties, we will not disclose your information to any other third party.</p>
<p><strong>IV.    YOUR RIGHTS OVER YOUR DATA</strong></p>
<p>In accordance with applicable privacy laws and to the extent that any information collected pursuant to the use of GrabDefence may constitute personal data, you may be entitled to access or update your personal data. Given that GrabDefence’s processing of your personal data is premised on GD Customers’ use of GrabDefence when you use their Digital Platforms, if you would like to exercise your rights, we recommend that you directly approach the operator of the Digital Platform you are using to obtain more information about how your information is used and processed, and to exercise your rights over your personal data.</p>
<p><strong>V.    RETENTION OF DATA</strong></p>
<p>We retain your information for as long as we have a business purpose (i.e. to provide GrabDefence, and to fulfil the Purposes) or legal purpose to do so. Once these purposes are satisfied, we take steps to destroy or anonymise your information.</p>
<p><strong>VI.    INTERNATIONAL TRANSFERS OF DATA</strong></p>
<p>Your information may be transferred from the country, state and city (“Home Country”) in which you are present while using GD Customers’ Digital Platforms to another country, state and city (“Alternate Country”).</p>
<p><strong>VII.    PROTECTION OF DATA</strong></p>
<p>We will take reasonable legal, organisational and technical measures to ensure that your information is protected. This includes measures to prevent data from getting lost, or used or accessed in an unauthorised way. We limit access to your information to our employees on a need to know basis. Those processing your data will only do so in an authorised manner and are required to treat your information with confidentiality. </p>
<p>Nevertheless, please understand that the transmission of information via the internet is not completely secure. Although we will do our best to protect your information, we cannot guarantee the security of your information transmitted through any online means, therefore, any transmission remains at your own risk. </p>
<p><strong>VIII.    AMENDMENTS AND UPDATES</strong></p>
<p>Grab shall have the right to modify, update or amend the terms of this Statement at any time by placing the updated Statement on its website.</p>
<p>If you have any queries about how your data is being used, please reach out to the GD Customer with whom you may be registered as a user. If you have other queries relating to GrabDefence, please contact our Data Privacy Officer via the form set out in the Privacy Notice.</p>
<!--EndFragment-->]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/privacy-notice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-06-21T11:08:03+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-06-21T11:08:03+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/lam-sao-de-publish-package-len-nuget-org/</id>
    <title>Làm sao để publish package lên Nuget.org</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h1 id="1-nuget-là-gì">1. Nuget là gì?</h1>
<p>Đã có người trả lời câu hỏi này rồi, nên bạn cứ coi ở đây: <a href="https://anhdung.me/2015/04/02/nuget-la-gi/">https://anhdung.me/2015/04/02/nuget-la-gi/ </a></p>
<p>Thật ra, nếu mà bạn không biết <a href="https://anhdung.me/2015/04/02/nuget-la-gi/">Nuget là gì</a> thì chắc cũng không cần phải coi thêm mấy bước sau chi nữa đâu.</p>
<h1 id="2-đăng-ký-tài-khoản-trên-nuget-org">2. Đăng ký tài khoản trên nuget.org</h1>
<p>Vào <a href="https://www.nuget.org/">https://www.nuget.org/</a> là xong thôi. Nuget hiện chỉ cần có Microsoft account (chẳng hạn như Office 365, các dịch vụ mail xưa nay hotmail/ outlook/ live) là có thể Signin vô được.</p>
<p>Signin vô được rồi thì click vô account name của mình, chọn mục API Keys rồi click Create để tạo key. Tạo xong nhớ copy để xuống bước 3 mình có mình xài nghen.</p>
<h1 id="3-build-code-và-publish">3. Build code và publish</h1>
<p>Cứ làm cái gì mình thích, bên dưới là một vài thứ hay ho bạn có thể thêm vào trong file csproj để hiển thị khi publish lên Nuget. Trong đó thuộc tính GenerateDocumentationFile sẽ cho phép giữ nguyên thông tin comment không bị mất.</p>
<description>My Awesome Package<description></description>
<generatedocumentationfile>true</generatedocumentationfile>
<packageid>AwesomePackage</packageid>
<version>1.0.0</version>
<authors>Fun Corp</authors>
<company>Fun Inc</company>

Sau khi xong xuôi thì Build lại project thử, build xong thì Pack. Giờ đây trong thư mục bin/Debug sẽ xuất hiện thêm file xxx.version.nupkg, đây chính là file bạn cần publish lên.

Giờ mở terminal lên, cd vô ngay thư mục vừa tạo ra file nupkg hồi nãy.

dotnet nuget push xxx.version.nupkg --api-key \[key hồi này mới copy] --source https://api.nuget.org/v3/index.json

# 4. Xong

Vô lại nuget.org chọn Manage Packages rồi coi package đã được duyệt và listed chưa. Trong này cũng có nhiều chỗ hay ho như là update lại thông tin Readme, bla bla bla...

**Hư Trúc**</description>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/lam-sao-de-publish-package-len-nuget-org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-06-02T08:55:14+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-06-02T08:55:14+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/controller-controllerbase-apicontroller/</id>
    <title>Controller, ControllerBase, ApiController</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<!--StartFragment-->
<p>Hồi đầu nhìn thấy có vẻ giống nhau, hơi lộn lẹo nên phải biên lại đây cho dễ nhớ.</p>
<p>Bạn sẽ nhìn thấy 3 class này khi khởi tạo dự án WebAPI (là <a href="http://ASP.NET">ASP.NET</a> Core Web API hoặc là <a href="http://ASP.NET">ASP.NET</a> Web Application (.NET Framework).</p>
<p>Theo đó thì trên .NET Framework API sẽ như bên dưới. Muốn thay đổi route thì phải chỉnh trong App_Start/WebApiConfig.cs</p>
<p><code>public class SampleAPIController : ApiController</code>\
<code>{</code>\
<code>// your code in here</code>\
<code>}</code></p>
<p>Còn trên NET Core thì tiện hơn có thể set route theo từng controller hoặc từng method luôn, khá là tiện dụng với annonation method.</p>
<p><code>[ApiController]</code>\
<code>[Router("[controller]")</code>\
<code>public class SampleAPIController : ControllerBase</code>\
<code>{</code>\
<code>// your code in here</code>\
<code>}</code></p>
<p>Còn Controller thì được dùng cho MVC web pages, tất nhiên rồi!</p>
<p>Tham khảo thêm ở đây: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/web-api/?view=aspnetcore-6.0"></a><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/web-api/?view=aspnetcore-6.0">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/web-api/?view=aspnetcore-6.0</a></p>
<!--EndFragment-->
<p>Hư Trúc</p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/controller-controllerbase-apicontroller/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-05-09T12:12:27+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-05-09T12:12:27+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/some-tricks-with-net-6-0/</id>
    <title>Some tricks with NET 6.0</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>IDE: Visual Studio 2022</p>
<h1 id="hide-warning-code">Hide Warning Code</h1>
<p>Open .csproject file, add this line below into the <code>&lt;PropertyGroup&gt;</code></p>
<p><code>&lt;NoWarn&gt;$(NoWarn);1591&lt;/NoWarn&gt;</code></p>
<p>In there: 1591 is the Code show in Error List</p>
<img src="/images/screenshot-2022-05-06-123556.e2982249e3e054db02f40028be9a16dd.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="258" height="223" />
<p><strong>Hư Trúc</strong></p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/some-tricks-with-net-6-0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-05-06T07:29:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-05-06T07:29:00+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/overloadable-operators/</id>
    <title>Overloadable operators</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>C# cho phép dùng operator với Class, Struct</p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp">public struct Complex
        {
            public double Real { get; set; }
            public double Imaginary { get; set; }

            public static Complex operator +(Complex c1, Complex c2)
            {
                return new Complex
                {
                    Real = c1.Real + c2.Real,
                    Imaginary = c1.Imaginary + c2.Imaginary
                };
            }
        }</code></pre>
<p><strong>Nhiếp Phong</strong></p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/overloadable-operators/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-04-06T11:17:09+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-04-06T11:17:09+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/dem-so-dong-code-line-of-code-loc/</id>
    <title>Đếm số dòng code (Line of Code, LOC)</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Nếu xài Visual Studio thì có cái tool Calculate Code Metrics trong menu Analyze.</p>
<p>Hoặc không thì mở Power Shell lên cd vô folder cần đếm rồi chạy, nhớ thêm/ xóa mấy cái file ext cần thiết nha.</p>
<p><strong><em>(gci -include .cs,.xaml,.js,.cshtml -recurse | select-string .).Count</em></strong></p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/dem-so-dong-code-line-of-code-loc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-04-05T04:03:25+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-04-05T04:03:25+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/lam-the-nao-de-dich-nguoc-decompile-reverse-engineering-android-apk/</id>
    <title>Làm thế nào để dịch ngược (decompile, reverse engineering) Android APK</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<!--StartFragment-->
<p>Có nhiều lý do để phải decompile một file APK trên Android, nếu bạn cần thì theo các bước sau đây và chỉ với 3 câu lệnh là xong.</p>
<p>Vì các tool này đều viết bằng Java nên đầu tiên là cài đặt Java 8, trang chủ <a href="https://www.java.com/en/"></a><a href="https://www.java.com/en/">https://www.java.com/en/</a> mấy chục năm rồi vẫn thế, chả có thay đổi gì. Trên Windows nếu cài xong mà chạy lệnh java -version không có gì thì nhớ thêm Path đến folder cài java trong System environment variables.</p>
<p>Xong rồi thì tải apktool về, coi hướng dẫn chi tiết trong này <a href="https://ibotpeaches.github.io/Apktool/install/"></a><a href="https://ibotpeaches.github.io/Apktool/install/">https://ibotpeaches.github.io/Apktool/install/</a>. Không nhất thiết phải move vào C:\Windows hay /usr/local/bin chi đâu, vẫn có thể chạy lệnh apktool từ chỗ khác được.</p>
<p>Sau khi đã rebuild file APK bằng lệnh thì chúng ta cần sign APK này mới có thể đem cài trên thiết bị được, tải nguyên cục này về <a href="https://github.com/techexpertize/SignApk"></a><a href="https://github.com/techexpertize/SignApk">https://github.com/techexpertize/SignApk</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Nhiếp Phong</strong></p>
<!--EndFragment-->]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/lam-the-nao-de-dich-nguoc-decompile-reverse-engineering-android-apk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-04-03T18:34:45+02:00</published>
    <updated>2022-04-03T18:34:45+02:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/taskbar-windows-10-tren-win11/</id>
    <title>Taskbar Windows 10 trên Win11</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Windows 11 ngon lành nhưng mà taskbar hơi chán, nhất là với ai xài màn hình rộng, độ phân giải cao muốn nhanh chóng thì đâu có ai phải rê chuột vô group rồi mới click. Vậy mà chả hiểu sao MS lại giấu luôn cái chức năng ungroup.</p>
<p>Có cái tool miễn phí ở đây <a href="https://github.com/valinet/ExplorerPatcher/releases">https://github.com/valinet/ExplorerPatcher/releases</a>, rất tuyệt vời, chỉ cần tải về rồi chạy file <em>ep_setup.exe</em> là xong.</p>
<p><strong>Phong Vân</strong></p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/taskbar-windows-10-tren-win11/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-03-23T04:50:39+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-23T04:50:39+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/lam-sao-de-google-chrome-auto-update-tren-ubuntu/</id>
    <title>Làm sao để Google Chrome auto update trên Ubuntu</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>First you have to install the key. This can be done by opening Terminal and typing</p>
<p><code>wget -q -O - https://dl-ssl.google.com/linux/linux_signing_key.pub | sudo apt-key add -</code></p>
<p>Step two is to add the repository</p>
<p><code>sudo sh -c 'echo "deb http://dl.google.com/linux/chrome/deb/ stable main" &gt;&gt; /etc/apt/sources.list.d/google-chrome.list'</code></p>
<p>Then you update and, if you haven't already, install Google Chrome</p>
<p><code>sudo apt-get update sudo apt-get install google-chrome-stable</code></p>
<p><strong>Phong Vân</strong></p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/lam-sao-de-google-chrome-auto-update-tren-ubuntu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-03-17T03:43:07+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-17T03:43:07+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/aws-sample-iot-data-generator/</id>
    <title>AWS Sample IoT Data Generator</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<!--StartFragment-->
<p>Có một cái ví dụ về việc giả lập dữ liệu IoT bắn ra từ các thiết bị ở đây: <a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/sbs-iot-data-generator">https://github.com/aws-samples/sbs-iot-data-generator</a></p>
<p>Mới đọc qua thì cũng hay, và thấy chỉ có duy nhất 1 file .py nên nghĩ là ale hấp cứ download về rồi chạy python <em>filename.py</em> là OK thôi, ai dè cũng lắm truân chuyên. Nên thôi lỡ rồi cũng gui lại đây để sau này tiện copy khi có cần nữa.</p>
<p>Mình triển khai trên Ubuntu 20.04.4 LTS, cần có những thứ này để tiếp tục:</p>
<ul>
<li>Amazon Web Services account: để lấy Access keys (access key ID and secret access key)</li>
<li>AWS Command Line Interface (CLI): chạy lệnh <code>aws configure</code> rồi điền các thông tin cần thiết, bao gồm Access key ở trên.</li>
<li>Python: phiên bản 2.7.18, giờ cài phiên bản 3.x chạy source này báo lỗi <code>SyntaxError: Missing parentheses in call to 'print'. Did you mean print(data)?</code></li>
<li>Pip2:</li>
</ul>
<p><code>sudo add-apt-repository universe sudo apt update curl &lt;https://bootstrap.pypa.io/pip/2.7/get-pip.py&gt; --output get-pip.py # Fetch get-pip.py for python 2.7 python2 get-pip.py pip2 --version</code></p>
<ul>
<li>boto3: <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-python/"></a><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-python/">https://aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-python/</a>, cài xong pip2 thì chạy <code>pip2 install boto3</code></li>
</ul>
<p>Sau khi setup xong thì chạy <code>python2 sbs.py</code> thôi.</p>
<p><strong>Phong Vân</strong></p>
<!--EndFragment-->]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/aws-sample-iot-data-generator/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-03-11T09:09:41+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-03-11T09:09:41+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/trien-khai-giai-phap-nfts-marketplace-tren-ha-tang-aws-sieu-nhanh/</id>
    <title>Triển khai giải pháp NFTs Marketplace trên hạ tầng AWS siêu nhanh</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<!--StartFragment-->
<h2 id="bối-cảnh">Bối cảnh</h2>
<p>Để hòa mình cùng phong trào Cách mạng Công nghiệp lần thứ tư (tiếng Tây kêu bằng: The Fourth Industrial Revolution, 4IR, or Industry 4.0) và sự chuyển mình của Thế giới cũng như đề cao tinh thần đi tắt đón đầu, đi sau về trước và nhanh chóng <del>lùa gà</del> phổ cập NFTs để đưa nước ta sánh vai cùng các cường quốc năm châu.</p>
<p>Từ những lý do cấp thiết trên, tui đã quyết định tìm giải pháp nhanh để triển khai nhanh NFTs Marketplace trên hạ tầng AWS, sau khi vọc xong thấy đúng là nhanh thật, thậm chí còn siêu nhanh nữa.</p>
<!-- excerpt -->
<p>Sở dĩ lựa AWS (hay các cloud provider khác cũng thế) là tại vì mấy người không biết gì như tui giờ già cả rồi thời gian nghiên cứu không còn nhiều, sức khỏe thì yếu không khiêng nổi mấy con server 4U 8U nhét vô rack cao hơn đầu người rồi lọ mọ cả buổi trong cái phòng có mười mấy độ với độ ẩm 50% nổi nữa, thành ra cứ lên mây cho sướng. Thiên hạ hay nói ba cái chuyện mây mưa sướng lắm, thật là sướng thật!</p>
<p>OK, vậy chúng ta sẽ xài Ethereum Ropsten Testnet với sự giúp sức đắc lực của Amazon Managed Blockchain cùng với lủ khủ một mớ mấy cái services khác phụ họa như hình minh họa bên dưới. Tất cả những services này đều được khởi tạo bằng CloudFormation.</p>
<p>Trong quá trình vọc vạch thì, tốn tiền nhất là Amazon Managed Blockchain vì xài On-Demand tính theo giờ, còn các services khác đều rơi vào free tier hết nên khá thoải mái. </p>
<img src="/assets/raudangdat.files.wordpress.com/2022/01/nft-marketplace-aws-architecture.f7cb97efde53e1abeacc6cb4bd0fbe26.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="821" height="527" />
<p>Hình của AWS Sample.</p>
<h2 id="bắt-đầu">Bắt đầu</h2>
<p>Kiểm tra phiên bản Nodejs, mấy phiên bản cũ quá không còn support hay gặp nhiều lỗi trời ơi đất hỡi lắm. Trên Ubuntu mặc định cài vô là bản 10.x, thành ra phải update hoặc lúc cài mới nhớ chú ý theo hướng dẫn này: <a href="https://thocode.net/blog/cai-dat-node-js-phien-ban-moi-nhat-tren-ubuntu-wsl2/"></a><a href="https://thocode.net/blog/cai-dat-node-js-phien-ban-moi-nhat-tren-ubuntu-wsl2/">https://thocode.net/blog/cai-dat-node-js-phien-ban-moi-nhat-tren-ubuntu-wsl2/</a></p>
<img src="/assets/raudangdat.files.wordpress.com/2022/01/cdk-nodejs-unsupport-version.bba5f5842671a686d7c2b5916e3af24c.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1053" height="300" />
<p>CDK không chạy được với các phiên bản Nodejs cũ.</p>
<p>Clone source và install dependencies</p>
<p><code>git clone https://github.com/aws-samples/simple-nft-marketplace.git</code></p>
<p><code>npm install</code></p>
<h2 id="deploy-contract">Deploy Contract</h2>
<p>Mình sẽ xài hardhat để deploy contract ERC721 viết bằng Solidity lên Ethereum Ropsten Testnet. Coi thêm ở <a href="https://hardhat.org/"></a><a href="https://hardhat.org/">https://hardhat.org/</a> nếu bạn quan tâm, cơ bản thì hardhat là môi trường phát triển của Ethereum, cũng như muốn code Java thì phải JDK hay làm .NET thì phải có .NET Framework hay .NET SDK vậy.</p>
<p>Chạy lệnh trong thư mục /contract</p>
<p><code>npm install</code></p>
<p><code>npx hardhat compile</code></p>
<h3 id="chạy-thử-trên-localhost">Chạy thử trên localhost</h3>
<p>Mở 2 terminal để giả bộ rằng một cái là server, còn cái kia là client tương tác với server.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cái đầu, chạy lệnh:</li>
</ul>
<p><code>npx hardhat node</code></p>
<p>Thấy hiện ra 20 cái Account và Private Key mỗi cái 10000 ETH là được, phải chi cái này đồ thiệt thì đã ha, tới đây nghỉ hưu được rồi rồi cần chi <del>lùa gà</del> mần mướn nữa. Nếu cần nhìn trực quan thì có thể dùng ví nào đó như MataMask/ Trust Wallet/ Phantom mở testnet network lên, chọn <a href="http://localhost/">Localhost</a> 8545 rồi import account test vô.</p>
<p><code>Account #0: 0xf39fd6e51aad88f6f4ce6ab8827279cfffb92266 (10000 ETH) Private Key: 0xac0974bec39a17e36ba4a6b4d238ff944bacb478cbed5efcae784d7bf4f2ff80</code></p>
<ul>
<li>Chuyển qua cái terminal 2, chạy:</li>
</ul>
<p><code>npx hardhat console --network localhost</code></p>
<p>Thấy hiện ra vầy là OK:</p>
<p><code>Contract deployed at 0x5FbDB2315678afecb367f032d93F642f64180aa3</code></p>
<p>Tiếp tục chạy lệnh này để mở hardhat console thực hiện việc sinh ra NFT token bằng SimpleERC721 nằm trong contract/contracts/SimpleERC721.sol</p>
<p><code>npx hardhat console --network localhost</code></p>
<p>Trong hardhat console chạy lần lượt, nhớ thay thế &lt;&gt; bằng address vừa hiện ra ở bên trên.</p>
<pre><code>const SimpleERC721 = await ethers.getContractFactory('SimpleERC721');
const contract = await SimpleERC721.attach('&lt;contract address&gt;');
await contract.newItem('dummy');</code></pre>
<p>Thấy vầy là OK:</p>
<img src="/assets/raudangdat.files.wordpress.com/2022/01/hardhat-contract-deploy.b239ee833f014468e851603bda0ce6de.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1011" height="704" />
<p>Quay lại MetaMask sẽ thấy đã tốn:</p>
<img src="/assets/raudangdat.files.wordpress.com/2022/01/metamask-localhost8545.1177aa8e244f123292a745b3663edef2.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="432" height="632" />
<p>Nếu nhìn trên terminal 1 (server) cũng sẽ thấy các thông tin thế này</p>
<img src="/assets/raudangdat.files.wordpress.com/2022/01/hardhat-server-terminal.9d154ecad68f8d6d2253c36e8059863f.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1138" height="181" />
<h3 id="chạy-thử-trên-ethereum-ropsten-testnet">Chạy thử trên Ethereum Ropsten Testnet</h3>
<p>Đăng nhập vô AWS Console &gt; Managed Blockchain &gt; Networks &gt; Ethereum Testnet Ropsten &gt; tạo một node &gt; copy HTTP Endpoint để thế vô lệnh này. Hết sức chú ý là phải có https nữa nha, tui gặp lỗi mò đã đời mới biết.</p>
<p><code>export AMB_HTTP_ENDPOINT='&lt;my-endpoint&gt;'</code></p>
<p>Tiếp tục tạo account để phục vụ cho việc deploy contract, đại khái acc này như là 20 acc có sẵn 10K ETH ở trên vậy nhưng có điều mới tạo thì không có đồng ETH nào nên muốn trả phí gas khi deploy thì giờ phải đi kiếm mấy cái Ropsten Faucet để gửi ít rETH vào ví. Cứ Google, nhiều trang làm được việc này, có trang thì dễ, có trang thì bắt phải giải captcha mới gửi cho.</p>
<p><code>npx hardhat account</code></p>
<p>Lấy thông tin vừa chạy ở trên bỏ vô đây</p>
<p><code>export PRIVATE_KEY='&lt;0x...&gt;'</code></p>
<p>Tiếp đến quay lại AWS Console vào Identity and Access Management (IAM) để tạo access key và scret access key. Chú ý là IAM bản cũ, chứ IAMv2 thì click nút Manage access keys để nó qua bản cũ nhe. Có thông tin thì điền vô đây:</p>
<p><code>export AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID='&lt;...&gt;' export AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY='&lt;...&gt;'</code></p>
<p>Chạy lệnh này để deploy với Amazon Managed Blockchain. (1).<code>npx hardhat run --network amb scripts/deploy-amb.js</code></p>
<p>Vì thư viện @aws\web3-http-provider\index.js đang để mặc định là us-east-1 nên nếu đang ở region khác sẽ gặp lỗi, cần phải set lại như bên dưới. Xong thì chạy lại file deploy-amb.js ở trên là được, thành công sẽ gặp dòng “Contract deployed at” và bị trừ tiền gas.</p>
<p><code>export AWS_DEFAULT_REGION='&lt;your-region&gt;'</code></p>
<h2 id="3-deploy-api-cho-backend">3. Deploy API cho Backend</h2>
<p>Cài đặt AWS CDK</p>
<p><code>npm install -g aws-cdk</code></p>
<p>Các lệnh bên dưới sẽ chạy trong thư mục /provision</p>
<p><code>npm install</code></p>
<p><code>export CONTRACT_ADDRESS='&lt;contract ở (1)&gt;'</code></p>
<p><code>cdk bootstrap</code></p>
<p>Chạy lệnh trên thì thằng CloudFormation sẽ tạo 1 stack là CDKToolkit để chuẩn bị cho việc deploy.</p>
<p><strong>Environment aws://*\</strong>/ap-southeast-1 bootstrapped.**</p>
<p>Chạy 3 lệnh này để vào-install dependencies-quay lại:</p>
<p><code>cd lambda; npm install; cd -;</code></p>
<p>Copy complied contract (SimpleERC721.json) vào /lambda/contracts/</p>
<p><code>cp ../contract/artifacts/contracts/SimpleERC721.sol/SimpleERC721.json lambda/contracts/.</code></p>
<p>Build CDK</p>
<p><code>npm run build</code></p>
<p>Check lại coi mấy biến môi trường set đúng chưa</p>
<p><code>echo $AMB_HTTP_ENDPOINT</code></p>
<p><code>echo $CONTRACT_ADDRESS</code></p>
<p>OK thì deploy, CloudFormation tiếp tục tạo stack SimpleNftMarketplaceStack.</p>
<p><code>cdk deploy SimpleNftMarketplaceStack</code></p>
<p>Như đã nói ngay khúc mở đầu, không chịu update Nodejs lên đúng phiên bản CDK được hỗ trợ nên gặp đủ thứ lỗi trời ơi đất hỡi ngay khúc giữa không, mà lúc đó lỡ làm rồi nên lại làm biếng làm lại từ đầu 😂</p>
<p>Số là đoạn này tui gặp lỗi vầy từ chiều, xong tui mò hoài không ra nên thôi tui đi ún gụ. Sau khi sin sỉn về vì chưa bù ngủ nên thôi tui mở máy lên tiếp rồi gõ tùm lum gì đó trong ba bốn cái terminal vừa mở ra, giờ chả nhớ đã gõ cái gì, vẫn không chạy được, thế là copy error log Google đại thì thấy trên Stackoverflow có ông nào đó trả lời về cái lỗi này cách đây 3 năm trước dù rằng nhìn đề bài thì có vẻ tay hỏi đang xài electron-builder gì đó, chưa kịp suy nghĩ coi có đúng cái mình cần không nữa, tui copy và paste vô đại, ai dè hết thấy lỗi, xong cái chạy CDK Deploy enter một phát được như là các thánh IT trong những đền thờ các huyền thoại vậy.</p>
<p>Trời đất quỷ thần thiên địa ơi, ghê vậy trời! 🤣</p>
<p>Nói chứ, lỗi vầy thì đúng là liên quan đến cục electron rồi.</p>
<p><code>Error: EACCES: permission denied, stat '/root/.cache/electron/8c5c987a73913c5646db497de9f6f9676033aa1586938d0d2c9cac8ac37f7e20/electron-v15.3.2-linux-x64.zip'</code></p>
<p>Vậy nên coi ở đây <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/51469367/electron-builder-eacces-permission-denied"></a><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/51469367/electron-builder-eacces-permission-denied">https://stackoverflow.com/questions/51469367/electron-builder-eacces-permission-denied</a> rồi cọp 2 lệnh này chạy, xong chạy lại cái cdk deploy là OK. Tuyệt vời phải không nào, cảm ơn Internet, cảm ơn ai đã mang Stackoverflow đến với thế giới loài người.</p>
<p><code>sudo npm uninstall -g electron</code></p>
<p><code>sudo npm install -g electron --unsafe-perm=true --allow-root</code></p>
<p>Sau khi chạy thành công thì sẽ có Output thế này <code>SimpleNftMarketplaceStack.NftApiEndpoint = https://***.execute-api.ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/prod/ SimpleNftMarketplaceStack.NftApiEndpoint8C6C6AD5 = https://***.execute-api.ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/prod/ SimpleNftMarketplaceStack.UserPoolClientId = *** SimpleNftMarketplaceStack.UserPoolId = ap-southeast-1*** Stack ARN: arn:aws:cloudformation:ap-southeast-1:***:stack/SimpleNftMarketplaceStack/***</code></p>
<h1 id="4-frontend">4. Frontend</h1>
<p>Phần này nằm trong thư mục /marketplace.</p>
<p>Chuyển vô thư mục /marketplace rồi set các biến môi trường như bên dưới.</p>
<pre><code>cat &lt;&lt;EOF &gt; .env.local
VUE_APP_AWS_REGION=&lt;region&gt;
VUE_APP_API_ENDPOINT=&lt;api-endpoint&gt;
VUE_APP_USER_POOL_ID=&lt;user-pool&gt;
VUE_APP_USER_POOL_WEB_CLIENT_ID=&lt;web-client&gt;
EOF</code></pre>
<p><code>sudo npm install</code></p>
<p>Không hiểu mình chạy thì lỗi “npm ERR! Response timeout while trying to fetch <a href="https://registry.npmjs.org/fs-extra"></a><a href="https://registry.npmjs.org/fs-extra">https://registry.npmjs.org/fs-extra</a> (over 30000ms)” nên phải</p>
<p><code>npm set timeout=100000</code></p>
<p>Sau đó thì phải chạy lệnh dưới để cho sạch chứ không thì lỗi “Unexpected end of JSON input while parsing near” nhìn rất là huyền bí.</p>
<p><code>npm cache clean --force</code></p>
<p>Giờ thì chạy OK rồi đó, hơi chậm. Chạy tiếp cái này</p>
<p><code>sudo npm run serve</code></p>
<p>Trường hợp lỗi liên quan đến vue-cli-service thì cài thêm dependence rồi chạy lại npm run serve.</p>
<p><code>npm i @vue/cli-service</code></p>
<p>Thấy báo địa chỉ Local với Network là OK, lấy browser mở ra vầy là coi như OK lần 2.</p>
<img src="/assets/raudangdat.files.wordpress.com/2022/01/nft-marketplace-frontend.87f482b7ed1e808ebc3925cec59f2c04.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="650" height="615" />
<p><a href="https://anhdung.me/">Anh Dũng</a>. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@theshubhamdhage?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Shubham Dhage</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/blockchain?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
<!--EndFragment-->]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/trien-khai-giai-phap-nfts-marketplace-tren-ha-tang-aws-sieu-nhanh/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-02-06T03:27:02+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-02-06T03:27:02+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/cai-dat-node-js-phien-ban-moi-nhat-tren-ubuntu-wsl2/</id>
    <title>Cài đặt Node.js phiên bản &quot;mới nhất&quot; trên Ubuntu WSL2</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Mặc định nếu cài đặt một cách truyền thống bằng lệnh sudo apt install nodejs thì chỉ có phiên bản 10.x, lý do vì đây là phiên bản “mới nhất” là thằng package manager apt này có được.</p>
<p>Trong khi hiện tại, trên trang chủ thì bản LTS là 16.x, có nhiều cách để cài bản mới nhất thiệt sự từ trang chủ, và đây là một trong những cách dễ nhất:</p>
<p><code>cd ~</code></p>
<p><code>curl -sL https://deb.nodesource.com/setup_16.x-o nodesource_setup.sh</code></p>
<p><code>sudo bash nodesource_setup.sh</code></p>
<p><code>sudo apt install nodejs</code></p>
<p>Xong, chỉ vậy thôi! Để kiểm tra coi phiên bản nào thì chạy</p>
<p><code>node -v</code></p>
<p><em>Phong Vân.</em></p>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/cai-dat-node-js-phien-ban-moi-nhat-tren-ubuntu-wsl2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-01-16T22:27:12+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-01-16T22:27:12+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/kinh-nghiem-thi-aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate-saa-c02/</id>
    <title>Kinh nghiệm thi AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Associate (SAA-C02)</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<!--StartFragment-->
<p>Tưởng tượng mớ kiến thức học mấy tháng qua y chang như là dưa kiệu ngâm ăn Tết vậy đó, mới làm xong nhận vô trong hủ thì ăn liền không có được vì nó chưa có thấm, chưa mềm, chưa lên men đủ… bla bla bla. Thành ra làm Practice Test mà không ổn thì nên nghỉ ngơi mấy bữa, chả buồn đụng tới thì mọi thứ có vẻ bắt đầu ổn dần, nhưng cũng đừng để lâu quá chua lét khỏi ăn nha!</p>
<!--EndFragment-->
<!-- excerpt -->
<!--StartFragment-->
<p>Tui mới thi xong nên biên mấy dòng trước là để ghi lại kỷ niệm lâu rồi mới ngồi lại học hành một cách gần gần nghiêm chỉnh, sau là để chia sẻ thêm thông tin với bà con.</p>
<h2 id="có-cần-mua-dump-không">Có cần mua dump không?</h2>
<p>Không cần!</p>
<p>Ban đầu cũng khá cân nhắc mấy chỗ như kiểu skillcertpro hoặc mấy ông bán dump bao đậu trên FB, mà thiệt tình là nhìn hên xui may rủi quá, không biết gốc gác từ đâu ra, coi một số dump mẫu trước khi mua thì phần giải thích đáp án khá sơ sài, chưa kể đề thi cũng updated hoài chứ đâu có như Tứ thư Ngũ kinh. Còn lý do chính là tui nhận ra tui hiện tại không thể học thuộc lòng nổi nữa rồi, vì có quá nhiều dịch vụ/ tình huống cần phải nhớ rồi. Nếu có thể nhớ hết được thì chắc là dump cũng có lợi.</p>
<p>Thiên hạ khen chê đủ kiểu:</p>
<h2 id="nên-đăng-ký-tài-khoản-aws-để-thực-hành-không">Nên đăng ký tài khoản AWS để thực hành không?</h2>
<p>Nên!</p>
<p>Chắc chắn là rất nên. Ban đầu, để đỡ mất thời gian cũng như suy nghĩ thiển cận rằng làm thiệt mà không để ý free tier thì mắc công bị charge tiền nữa nên hầu như tui đều bỏ qua hết mấy phần Hands On và hậu quả là sau khi đi luyện mấy bài Practice Test có nhiều câu tui làm sai tới 4 lần luôn, đỉnh cao tới mức đã ghi lại, vẽ mind map mà do quá nhiều thứ để nhớ nên cuối cùng không thể nhớ nỗi thứ đó là thứ nào.</p>
<p>Và cuối cùng thì phần nào mà không cách nào nhớ nỗi tui đi kiếm sample/ tutorial coi để thực hành lại, nhìn thấy được kết quả thiệt nó chạy thế nào sau khi mình lắp ghép mớ đồ hàng của AWS chính là cách tốt nhất để nhớ dịch vụ đó nó làm cái gì, gắn với cái gì trong tình huống nào.</p>
<p>Sau khi làm Hands On xong thì nhớ dọn dẹp sạch sẽ là được. Để an tâm hơn thì cũng nên set Billing Budgets cho khỏi lo xài quá trớn.</p>
<h2 id="tui-đã-luyện-bằng-cách-nào">Tui đã luyện bằng cách nào?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Học trên Udemy: khóa Ultimate AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate 2021 (giờ thấy đã cập nhật lên 2022 rồi) của Stephane Maarek: <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate-saa-c02/"></a><a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate-saa-c02/">https://www.udemy.com/course/aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate-saa-c02/</a></li>
<li>Luyện thêm khóa Practice bằng khóa Practice Exams | AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (<a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/practice-exams-aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate/"></a><a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/practice-exams-aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate/">https://www.udemy.com/course/practice-exams-aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate/</a>). Tui thấy khóa này khá ổn, cover đầy đủ kiến thức để đi thi, mấy bài Parctice giải thích đáp án cũng rất rõ ràng, chịu khó đọc hết là được, chưa kể là có update thường xuyên. Ngoài ra còn coi lẻ tẻ ở <a href="http://examptopics.com/">examptopics.com</a> cũng như là khóa AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate Practice Tests (SAA-C02) + Exam Simulator + Explanations + AWS Cheat Sheets của Neal Davis cũng trên Udemy.</li>
<li>Ghi notes, vẽ mind map. Tui share cái mind map của tui ở đây, chắc chắn là ở trỏng còn sai tè le, đừng có tin nha.</li>
<li>Thực hành thực tế lại những phần không hiểu, câu nào làm sai vài ba lần thì lôi mấy cái services ở trong ra đem hands on đúng tình huống trong câu hỏi đó luôn.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="đăng-ký-thi-kiểu-gì">Đăng ký thi kiểu gì?</h2>
<p>AWS họ có 2 đối tác khảo thí là PSI và Pearson VUE, cả 2 chỗ này đều có 2 hình thức là thi tại trung tâm liên kết (Testing Center) và thi online (Online Proctor), do đã có <a href="https://anhdung.me/2022/01/09/trai-nghiem-dang-ky-pearson-vue-online-proctor-thi-aws/">trải nghiệm khá là ba trợn với Pearson VUE online</a> nên sau khi được refund tui quyết định quay về với truyền thống, đăng ký thi ở Testing Center là partner với Pearson VUE (chọn Pearson VUE là vì cứ tưởng hơn PSI được 10p ai dè tới chừng vô thi mới biết 10p đó để làm survey sau khi thi xong, đúng là đánh lận con đen thiệt chớ).</p>
<p>Tất nhiên, lần tới nữa nếu có điều kiện thì tui vẫn muốn thử Online Proctor coi thế nào, còn đây là những cái lợi nếu ở Testing Center mà Online Proctor không có được:</p>
<ul>
<li>Không phải lo lắng việc check-in, ở xứ mình thì chỉ cần cầm theo CMND/ CCCD là được, điền tên ký tên bằng mẹ đẻ hết. Ngược lại thì: nếu Testing Center ở xa quá thì mắc công lo kẹt xe, đi lại các kiểu, tuy nhiên ở xứ mình nếu việc đi Sài Gòn, Đà Nẵng, Hà Nội không thành vấn đề với bạn thì cũng chẳng có gì phải lo luôn.</li>
<li>Mấy cái Testing Center cơ sở vật chất khá ổn, thậm chí mình còn coi được hình phòng thi trước nếu quá lo lắng máy móc không quen.</li>
<li>Khỏi lo dọn dẹp cái bàn để thi, cũng như là việc có ai đó vô tình kêu mình hoặc là bà bán cá đầu xóm bỗng dưng xắn quần lên chửi ông bán trứng um sùm. Thấy nhiều người review giám thị online bắt họ dẹp cả máy PS cùng mấy thứ linh tinh khác nữa.</li>
<li>Không như thi Online thì bị bắt nhìn chầm chầm thẳng vô Webcam, không được liếc chỗ khác, không được rời khỏi webcam trong suốt thời gian thi, không được dùng tay che miệng, không đọc câu hỏi thì thầm… bla bla bla… Khá là khó nhưng kể ra cũng đúng, tại giám thị online chỉ nhìn được qua mỗi cái webcam thôi.</li>
<li>Và quan trọng là khi có sự cố (như máy tính ngủm củ tỏi, ve chai cắt dây mạng bán đồng nát…) thì ít ra ngay lúc đó có người xử lý/ giải quyết/ hoặc ghi nhận sự việc chứ không có nói kiểu “Lỗi mạng” mà chả biết mạng ai lỗi. Tất nhiên, có một điều chắc chắn rằng mọi thứ đều không chắc chắn, nên thôi lo quá cũng chả làm được gì.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="có-tips-nào-không">Có tips nào không?</h2>
<p>Có!</p>
<ul>
<li>Phải nhìn ra các từ khóa trong câu hỏi như là: minimize the costs, managed services, high read/ disaster recovery, reusable, SaaS… để xác định được tình huống cần giải quyết, loại bỏ các phương án không cần thiết cho đỡ mất thời gian.</li>
<li>Có nhiều tình huống đáp án khá là đơn giản, đừng thần thánh hóa giải pháp làm gì cho sai.</li>
<li>Tham gia cộng đồng nào đó có cùng mục tiêu với mình, đọc mấy kinh nghiệm của người vừa thi xong cũng đỡ bỡ ngỡ. Có khá nhiều cộng đồng như vậy trên Facebook Group, Reddit thậm chí cả Telegram nữa.</li>
<li>Tìm được ai/ hoặc nhóm học chung và có thời gian cố định hàng tuần thì rất hữu ích để chống lại sự làm biếng.</li>
<li>Nhớ request ESL trước khi thi để được thêm 30p, tổng cộng là 160p cũng đỡ lắm. Cái này ai cũng biết nhưng hay quên hoặc là chưa được Approve mà đã đăng ký thi!</li>
<li>Tưởng tượng mớ kiến thức học mấy tháng qua y chang như là dưa kiệu ngâm ăn Tết vậy đó, mới làm xong nhận vô trong hủ thì ăn liền không có được vì nó chưa có thấm, chưa mềm, chưa lên men đủ… bla bla bla. Thành ra làm Practice Test mà không ổn thì nên nghỉ ngơi mấy bữa, chả buồn đụng tới thì mọi thứ có vẻ bắt đầu ổn dần, nhưng cũng đừng để lâu quá chua lét khỏi ăn nha!</li>
</ul>
<!--EndFragment-->]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/kinh-nghiem-thi-aws-certified-solutions-architect-associate-saa-c02/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-01-09T18:51:46+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-01-09T18:51:46+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/trai-nghiem-dang-ky-pearson-vue-online-proctor-thi-aws/</id>
    <title>Trải nghiệm đăng ký Pearson VUE Online Proctor thi AWS</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Tui đẻ ra ở thời Web 1.0 rồi lớn lên đi mần, kiếm ăn nhờ Web 2.0, bây giờ là kỷ nguyên Web 3.0 của metaverse gì gì đó nên tui rất có niềm tin vào mọi thứ sẽ được “trực tuyến hóa” một cách tuyệt vời. Nhưng rồi sau trải nghiệm tồi tệ lần đầu tiên, cũng như thấy được cơ số chuyện ba trợn xảy đến với mọi người nên thôi tui quyết định quay về với truyền thống, đăng ký thi ở Testing Center…</p>
<!-- excerpt -->
<!--StartFragment-->
<p>Tui còn nhớ bữa đó làm xong bài thi thử thấy kết quả đủ PASS nên lật đật bay vô đăng ký thi thiệt luôn ngay trong đêm để cho kịp cái hên, trong bụng còn tính coi có ca thi nào sớm nhất thì đăng ký luôn khỏi cần tắm rửa chi ráo để giữ cái hên mới làm xong bài test hồi nãy.</p>
<p>Chuyện là…</p>
<p>AWS họ có 2 đối tác khảo thí là PSI và Pearson VUE, coi thử 2 bên thì thấy PSI thua 10 phút, với bữa mới thấy topic trên Reddit kêu Do not use PSI testing nữa nên tất nhiên mặc định Pearson VUE ngon lành rồi, đăng ký ngay và luôn thôi. OK, xong, mọi thứ hoàn toàn tự động hóa thật tuyệt vời.</p>
<p>Tối đó, tui chạy test session trước, mọi thứ vẫn rất tuyệt vời, rồi dọn dẹp bàn ghế các kiểu, cất bớt điện thoại, thiết bị điện tử khác, giấy tờ sổ sách trên bàn… còn mấy cái màn hình lỡ gắn vô arm rồi nên khá là nan giải, định bụng sẽ trùm lại hoặc hỏi giám thị. Lịch thi bảo mở cổng check-in trước giờ thi 30p thì 45p trước đó là tui đã ngồi F5 từ từ luôn, không biết có phải tại tui bấm F5 nhiều quá mà làm hệ thống ngủm củ tỏi không nữa, nhưng ngạc nhiên chưa kìa: hệ thống thi ngủm thiệt.</p>
<p>Thử đi thử lại mấy lần toàn báo lỗi ngay chỗ màn hình Network check 75%, coi chi tiết thì biết được là không kết nối được tới một dịch vụ nào đó của Wowza, chèn ơi hết gần 10p bà nó của tui rồi mà chưa check-in được, trong khi cái app OnVUE này nó dùng công nghệ đỉnh cao gì đó mà mỗi lần load cũng tốn hết mấy chục giây của tui, chưa kể trước đó còn phải đánh vật để tắt cái process dbxsvc nữa trong khi hồi chạy test thì không thấy nói năng gì. Và tui đã cẩn thận tới mức hồi chạy test OK xong là không tắt máy, không dám nhúc nhích cái laptop luôn.</p>
<p>OK, dù sao thì phận end-user mà, bằng mọi giá phải check-in được để vô thi chứ, 150 Biden cùng mấy tháng trời từ bỏ mọi lạc thú trần gian chạy tịnh gìn giữ tiết hạnh để ôn luyện mà. Tui đổi qua cái máy khác, đổi luôn line Internet khác, cũng không được thì đổi qua tới 4G Mobifone, rồi tới 4G I-Tel, rồi để chắc ăn ăn hơn trong trường hợp toàn cõi An Nam tự nhiên chặn bọn Wowza vì lý do trời ơi nào đó nên tui thử cả VPN ở nước khác. Cũng không được luôn, lúc này chỉ còn 1 phút nữa là hết giờ check-in!</p>
<p>Tâm trạng hết sức rối bời, thất vọng cùng cực tui chat với Support thì gặp được con Bot hết sức lịch sự hỏi tên, hỏi ID, số điện thoại đồ rồi kêu tui đợi để nó đi kiếm con người. Với bản tính là con người nên tất nhiên không phải đồng loại thì tui càng nghi ngờ hơn, nên làm sao tui tin được con Bot này, tui quay qua máy khác kiếm Support, cũng gặp tiếp Bot. Đợi mấy chục phút và dòm màn hình trong tuyệt vọng và lúc này mới cảm thấy tự động hóa thật kinh hoàng, dù rằng mới mấy tiếng trước tui còn thấy nó tuyệt vời thế nào.</p>
<p>Lần mò một hơi tui mới kiếm ra chỗ để gửi mail bày tỏ nỗi thất vọng và tức thì nhận được cái mail Automatic reply càng làm tui ức chế tợn, còn số điện thoại thì tất nhiên là xứ ta không có line riêng rồi, bên Úc sẽ lo mà đêm hôm giờ thì làm gì còn ai trực điện thoại nữa.</p>
<p>Lúc đó bực nhất là khi mà tui tưởng tượng thi online với giám thị ở tận xứ nào đó trên trái đất này làm cho khá lo lắng và bỏ công chuẩn bị đủ thứ, cuối cùng thì vì một cái lỗi ất ơ nào đó của một cái hệ thống khỉ gió trong cái quy trình nhì nhằng làm tui chả biết mình đang bị cái củ-cải gì đó với mấy dòng thông báo lỗi chung chung vô hồn, cơ quan chủ quản thì im ru, không email, không chat, không thông báo để mọi người phải lên mạng xã hội chửi, dạo vòng vòng thì hóa ra cũng đầy người như mình từ nhiều quốc gia khác nhau. Ai đời đối tác khảo thí một cái môn để làm những giải pháp hạ tầng với những từ khóa mỹ miều như là always on, disaster recovery, high availability… bla bla bla… Cùng cam kết dịch vụ (SLA) cao nhất mà một trong số các services của họ lại ngủm củ tỏi, không một lời thông báo, không một con người nào trả lời email, chat support. Chỉ toàn những cái email hay Help Bot với tiêu đề “Automatic reply” vô hồn phản hồi ngay lập tức và sau vài tiếng đồng hồ chờ đợi trong vô vọng, càng làm cho mọi người càng bực bội hơn nữa.</p>
<p>Nhưng dù sao, tạm bỏ qua những điều ức chế bên trên thì mặt khác cũng cho tui được trải nghiệm rằng mọi cam kết về dịch vụ chỉ là cam kết thôi, còn chết thì phải chết làm sao mà tránh khỏi được. Có một điều chắc chắn rằng mọi thứ đều không chắc chắn mà :))</p>
<p>Sau hơn 4 tiếng đồng hồ bị sự cố thì cuối cùng Pearson VUE cũng có email báo lại họ “gặp khó khăn về mặt kỹ thuật” và bảo sẽ cancel lịch thi cũng như refund.</p>
<p>Tui đẻ ra ở thời Web 1.0 rồi lớn lên đi mần, kiếm ăn nhờ Web 2.0, bây giờ là kỷ nguyên Web 3.0 của metaverse gì gì đó nên tui rất có niềm tin vào mọi thứ sẽ được “trực tuyến hóa” một cách tuyệt vời. Nhưng rồi sau trải nghiệm tồi tệ lần đầu tiên, cũng như thấy được cơ số chuyện ba trợn xảy đến với mọi người nên thôi tui quyết định quay về với truyền thống, đăng ký thi ở Testing Center vì ngoài trải nghiệm tồi tệ vừa rồi thì dạo dạo trên mạng thấy cũng có nhiều người than phiền:</p>
<ul>
<li>Một sự trùng hợp ngẫu nhiên chưa được thống kê từ rất nhiều thành viên trên Reddit cho rằng mặc dù là 24/7 nhưng nếu đặt lịch thi vào cuối tuần hoặc khuya lơ khuya lắc thì mấy tay proctor có vẻ khá khó tính. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AWSCertifications/comments/q0fu4t/comment/hf9mzju/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3"></a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AWSCertifications/comments/q0fu4t/comment/hf9mzju/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">https://www.reddit.com/r/AWSCertifications/comments/q0fu4t/comment/hf9mzju/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3</a></li>
<li>Đang thi xui xui Dropbox nó mở process lên là a-lê-hấp vi phạm quy định nhé bấy-bì! Ơ thế cái app OnVue để làm cái khỉ khô gì mà không control được, hoặc yêu cầu reset luôn OS trước khi bắt đầu thi đi. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AWSCertifications/comments/q0fu4t/comment/hf7s9aa/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3"></a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AWSCertifications/comments/q0fu4t/comment/hf7s9aa/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">https://www.reddit.com/r/AWSCertifications/comments/q0fu4t/comment/hf7s9aa/?utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3</a></li>
<li>Nửa năm trước họ cũng gặp “gặp khó khăn về mặt kỹ thuật” y chang lần này: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CompTIA/comments/p19ib9/anybody_else_have_technical_issues_with_onvue/"></a><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CompTIA/comments/p19ib9/anybody_else_have_technical_issues_with_onvue/">https://www.reddit.com/r/CompTIA/comments/p19ib9/anybody_else_have_technical_issues_with_onvue/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Kế hoạch chốt năm bằng cái chứng chỉ AWS không kịp thực hiện, qua tuần sau thì tui đăng ký ở Testing Center.</p>
<p>Ban đầu thấy review của mấy bạn Tây nói tới testing center thì dễ bị stresses hơn, do không khí phòng thi, do khác cái bàn quen thuộc… Nhưng hình như với mình thì lại thấy dễ chịu hơn, đôi khi còn cảm giác thú vị vì được sống lại cái không khí của chục năm về trước, âu chắc cũng là một trong những lợi thế hiếm hoi của dân châu Á bị ép học hành với thi cử liên miên hồi còn nhỏ.</p>
<p>Ở Testing Center thì mọi thứ khá suôn sẻ, thậm chí còn được alo hỏi có muốn thi sớm hông vì cán bộ phòng thi mắc đi chích mũi 3.</p>
<p><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jeshoots?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">JESHOOTS.COM</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/online-exam?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em>
<em>.</em></p>
<!--EndFragment-->]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/trai-nghiem-dang-ky-pearson-vue-online-proctor-thi-aws/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2022-01-09T06:32:58+01:00</published>
    <updated>2022-01-09T06:32:58+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/princess-mononoke/</id>
    <title>Thử nghiệm Princess Mononoke</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong><em>Princess Mononoke</em></strong> (<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_language">Japanese</a>: もののけ姫 <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hepburn_romanization">Hepburn</a>: <strong>Mononoke-<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hime">hime</a></strong>, &quot;Spirit/Monster Princess&quot;) is a 1997 Japanese <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anime">animated</a> <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fantasy_film">fantasy film</a> written and directed by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hayao_Miyazaki">Hayao Miyazaki</a>, animated by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Studio_Ghibli">Studio Ghibli</a> for <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tokuma_Shoten">Tokuma Shoten</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nippon_Television_Network">Nippon Television Network</a> and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dentsu">Dentsu</a>, and distributed by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toho">Toho</a>. The film stars the voices of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yōji_Matsuda">Yōji Matsuda</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuriko_Ishida">Yuriko Ishida</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yūko_Tanaka">Yūko Tanaka</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaoru_Kobayashi_(actor)">Kaoru Kobayashi</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masahiko_Nishimura">Masahiko Nishimura</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsunehiko_Kamijo">Tsunehiko Kamijo</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akihiro_Miwa">Akihiro Miwa</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitsuko_Mori">Mitsuko Mori</a> and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hisaya_Morishige">Hisaya Morishige</a>.</p>
<!-- excerpt -->
<p><em>Princess Mononoke</em> is set in the late <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muromachi_period">Muromachi period</a> (approximately 1336 to 1573) of Japan with fantasy elements. The story follows the young <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emishi">Emishi</a> prince Ashitaka's involvement in a struggle between the gods of a forest and the humans who consume its resources. The term &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mononoke">Mononoke</a>&quot; (<a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/物の怪">物の怪</a>) or もののけ is not a name, but a Japanese word for a spirit or monster: supernatural, shape-shifting beings.</p>
<p>The film was released in Japan on July 12, 1997, and in the United States on October 29, 1999. It was a critical and commercial <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockbuster_(entertainment)">blockbuster</a>, becoming the highest-grossing film in Japan of 1997, and also held Japan's box office record for domestic films until 2001's <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spirited_Away">Spirited Away</a></em>, another Miyazaki film. It was <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dubbing_(filmmaking)">dubbed</a> into English and distributed in North America by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miramax">Miramax</a>, and despite a poor box office performance there, it sold well on DVD and video, greatly increasing Ghibli's popularity and influence outside Japan.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Source: <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princess_Mononoke">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princess_Mononoke</a></p>
</blockquote>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/princess-mononoke/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2020-03-09T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2020-03-09T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/daft-punk/</id>
    <title>Daft Punk</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>Daft Punk</strong> is a French <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_music">electronic music</a> duo formed in Paris in 1993 by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy-Manuel_de_Homem-Christo">Guy-Manuel de Homem-Christo</a> and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Bangalter">Thomas Bangalter</a>. They achieved popularity in the late 1990s as part of the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_house">French house</a> movement; they also had success in the years following, combining elements of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_music">house music</a> with <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Funk">funk</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Techno">techno</a>, <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disco">disco</a>, rock and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synthpop">synthpop</a>. They have worn ornate helmets and gloves to assume <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robot">robot</a> personas in most public appearances since 1999 and rarely grant interviews or appear on television. The duo were managed from 1996 to 2008 by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Winter">Pedro Winter</a> (also known as Busy P), the head of <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Banger_Records">Ed Banger Records</a>.</p>
<!-- excerpt -->
<p>After Bangalter and Homem-Christo's <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indie_rock">indie rock</a> band <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darlin&#039;_(French_band)">Darlin'</a> disbanded, they began experimenting with <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drum_machine">drum machines</a> and synthesisers. Their debut studio album <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homework_(Daft_Punk_album)">Homework</a></em> was released by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgin_Records">Virgin Records</a> in 1997 to positive reviews, backed by singles &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Around_the_World_(Daft_Punk_song)">Around the World</a>&quot; and &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Da_Funk">Da Funk</a>&quot;. Their second album, <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discovery_(Daft_Punk_album)">Discovery</a>,</em> had further success, supported by hit singles &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_More_Time_(Daft_Punk_song)">One More Time</a>&quot;, &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Love_(Daft_Punk_song)">Digital Love</a>&quot; and &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harder,_Better,_Faster,_Stronger">Harder, Better, Faster, Stronger</a>&quot;. In March 2005, Daft Punk released their third album, <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_After_All">Human After All</a>,</em> to mixed reviews, though the singles &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robot_Rock_(song)">Robot Rock</a>&quot; and &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technologic">Technologic</a>&quot; achieved success in the United Kingdom. Daft Punk <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alive_2006/2007">toured throughout 2006 and 2007</a> and released the live album <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alive_2007">Alive 2007</a></em>, which won a <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy_Award">Grammy Award</a> for <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy_Award_for_Best_Electronic/Dance_Album">Best Electronic/Dance Album</a>. They composed the score for the film <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tron:_Legacy">Tron: Legacy</a></em>, which was released in 2010 alongside <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tron:_Legacy_(soundtrack)">its soundtrack album</a>.</p>
<p>In 2013, Daft Punk left Virgin for <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia_Records">Columbia Records</a>, and released their fourth album, <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random_Access_Memories">Random Access Memories</a>,</em> to acclaim; lead single &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Get_Lucky_(Daft_Punk_song)">Get Lucky</a>&quot; reached the top 10 in the charts of 32 countries. <em>Random Access Memories</em> won five Grammy Awards in 2014, including <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy_Award_for_Album_of_the_Year">Album of the Year</a> and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy_Award_for_Record_of_the_Year">Record of the Year</a> for &quot;Get Lucky&quot;. In 2016, Daft Punk gained their first number one on the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billboard_Hot_100"><em>Billboard</em> Hot 100</a> with the song &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starboy_(song)">Starboy</a>&quot;, a collaboration with <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Weeknd">The Weeknd</a>. As of 2015, Daft Punk had sold over 12 million albums worldwide.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Source: <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daft_Punk">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daft_Punk</a></p>
</blockquote>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/daft-punk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2020-02-05T15:43:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2020-02-05T15:43:00+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/doom/</id>
    <title>Doom</title>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong><em>Doom</em></strong> (stylized as <strong><em>DOOM</em></strong> or <strong><em>DooM</em></strong> in other media) is a 1993 <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-person_shooter">first-person shooter</a> developed and published by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Id_Software">id Software</a> for <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/MS-DOS">MS-DOS</a>. Players assume the role of a <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_marine">space marine</a>, popularly known as &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doomguy">Doomguy</a>&quot;, fighting his way through hordes of invading <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demon">demons</a> from <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hell">Hell</a>. The first episode, comprising nine levels, was distributed freely as <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shareware">shareware</a> and played by an estimated 15–20 million people within two years; the full game, with two further episodes, was sold via <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mail_order">mail order</a>. An updated version with an additional episode, <em>Ultimate Doom</em>, was released in 1995 and sold at retail.</p>
<!-- excerpt -->
<p>Along with its predecessor <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfenstein_3D">Wolfenstein 3D</a></em>, <em>Doom</em> helped define the FPS genre and inspired numerous similar games, known as &quot;<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_clone"><em>Doom</em> clones</a>&quot;. It is one of the most significant games in <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_game_history">video game history</a>, and is frequently cited as one of the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greatest_video_games_of_all_time">greatest games of all time</a>. It pioneered <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Online_distribution">online distribution</a> and technologies including <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/3D_computer_graphics">3D graphics</a>, networked <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiplayer_video_game">multiplayer gaming</a>, and support for customized <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modification_(video_game)">modifications</a> via packaged files (<a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_WAD">WADs</a>). Its graphic violence and hellish imagery also made it the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_game_controversy">subject of controversy</a>, however.</p>
<p><em>Doom</em> has been <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Official_versions_of_Doom">ported to numerous platforms</a>. The <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(franchise)"><em>Doom</em> franchise</a> continued with <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_II:_Hell_on_Earth">Doom II: Hell on Earth</a></em> (1994) and <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expansion_pack">expansion packs</a> including <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_Levels_for_Doom_II">Master Levels for Doom II</a></em> (1995). The <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source_code">source code</a> was released in 1997, inspiring further adaptations. Id returned to the franchise with <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_3">Doom 3</a></em> (2004), a horror-focused retelling using the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Id_Tech_4">id Tech 4</a> engine, followed by a 2005 <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(film)"><em>Doom</em> film</a>. A 2016 reboot also titled <em><a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(2016_video_game)">Doom</a>,</em> powered by <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Id_Tech_6">id Tech 6</a>, returned to the fast-paced action of the first games.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Source: <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(1993_video_game">https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(1993_video_game</a>)</p>
</blockquote>]]>
    </content>
    <link href="https://cecilapp.github.io/the-butler/blog/doom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <published>2019-12-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  </entry>
</feed>
